Guide to the Ernest Werner Lennart papers 1941-1968
Western Washington University, Center for Pacific Northwest Studies
Ernest Werner Lennart papers
1941-1968
Center for Pacific Northwest Studies Goltz-Murray Building 808 25th St Bellingham, WA 98225-9123 Phone: 360 650 7534 Email: cpnws@wwu.edu
XOE_CPNWS0180Lennart
Lennart, Ernest Werner
1.5 linear ft.
The collection documents the personal life and political activities of Ernest Werner Lennart, a Whatcom County farmer who also served in the Washington State Legislature from 1941 to 1967. Materials include correspondence, legislative reports, files related to state legislation, speeches and essays, newspaper clippings, and records of Lennart's farm operation.
Ernest Werner Lennart was born in Sweden in 1893, emigrated to the United States in 1913, and served in the Army during World War I. He attended college upon his return from service and was married in 1920. The Lennart family eventually moved to the Pacific Northwest and settled in Everson, Washington, where Ernest worked in farming, cold storage, and the feed business.
Lennart was a member of the Freemasons, the American Legion, Veterans of Foreign Wars, and the Grange and Farm Bureau. He also served on the Mt. Baker Union School District board, chaired the Whatcom County Republican Central Committee, was Commissioner of the Whatcom County Public Utility District, and represented the 41st District in Whatcom County as a representative and senator between 1941 and 1967.
The Ernest Werner Lennart papers comprise personal and professional correspondence, legislative reports, files related to state legislation, speeches and essays, newspaper clippings, committee materials, and records from the operation of Lennart's farm from 1953 to 1967.
Topics of possible interest to researchers include state taxation issues including property taxes, joint tenancy, and funding for education, Indian treaties and fisheries rights, the Washington State Dairy Products Stabilization Act, Alien Land Law, the Washington State College Foundation, the Implied Consent Bill, and the the Washington State Arts Commission.
The collection is open to the public.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Lennart, Ernest Werner--Archives.
Washington (State)--Legislature--Senate.
Washington (State)--Law and legislation--History--Sources.; Washington (State)--Politics and government--History--Sources.
Agriculture--Washington (State)--Whatcom County--History--Sources.; Legislators--Washington (State)--History--Sources.
Records (Documents)
Washington (State)
- Memorial resolutions, undated (Box-folder 1/1)
- Election certificate, 1960 (Box-folder 1/2)
- Miscellaneous correspondence - peronal letter from Lennart's children; letters to the editor of the Bellingham Herald; letters exchanging praise between Lennart and other government officials, 1941-1965 (Box-folder 1/3)
- Correspondence re: Indian Fisheries - copy of treaty with Duwamish, Suquamish in Washington Territory naming cession of lands and establishment of reservations; exchange with Warren Magnuson, U.S. Senator, regarding efforts to modify or terminate Indian treaties and fisheries rights, 1855; circa 1962-1965 (Box-folder 1/4)
- Correspondence with Patricia Martin, freelance writer, near the end of Lennart's life, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 1/5)
- Correspondence with constituents re: increases in legislators' expense allowances (per diem), pay raises and pensions, 1965 (Box-folder 1/6)
- Personal correspondence - poetry by Eric H. Johnson; redistricting Washington State; retirement of state employees; farewell letters and speech, 1965-1968 (Box-folder 1/7)
- Correspondence with Washington State representatives re: secondhand knowledge of perjury committed by Freeman, then U.S. Secretary of Agriculture (Ralph Matter), 1962 (Box-folder 1/8)
- Correspondence re: levying taxes on intangible property; proposed Bainbridge Island-Fort Lawton Bridge; financing for school systems, 1953 (Box-folder 1/9-1/11)
- Correspondence re: the 1967 legislative session, 1967 January-April (Box-folder 1/12-1/18)
- Correspondence re: Senate Bill 79 (Dairy Bill) which was sponsored by Senator Lennart - bill would correct structure of the 1937 Milk Stabilization Act to support individual dairy farmers by stabilizing prices against large corporations, 1967 January-April (Box-folder 1/19)
- Correspondence re: funding education, 1967 (Box-folder 1/20)
- Correspondence re: highways, including Implied Consent Bill which would authorize Washington State Patrol to stop motorists to inspect drivers' licenses and operational state of the vehicle, designed to detect drivers under the influence of alcohol; efforts to weaken the Billboard Control Act of 1961, 1967 (Box-folder 1/21)
- Constitutional Revision Committee Report to Governor Daniel J. Evans - committee formed to explore means of amending the original Washington State Constitution to update the legal structure of state government, 1967 (Box-folder 1/22)
- Washington State Parks and Recreation Committee progress report - covered departmental developments from 1950-1960, a brief history of the department, and 20-year plan for the future, 1961 (Box-folder 1/23)
- Attorney General opinions, 1966 January-1967 August (Box-folder 1/24)
- Court papers - Thigpen v. Meyers, 1963 (Box-folder 1/25)
- Washington State Dairy Products Stabilization Act - text of bill written by Senator Lennart, 1967 (Box-folder 1/26)
- Miscellaneous legislation, circa 1965-1967 (Box-folder 1/27-1/28)
- Essays re: agriculture and supporting agriculture as a profession and way of life, undated (Box-folder 1/29)
- Essays in support of amending the Alien Land Law to encourage the construction of the Shell Oil Refinery, undated (Box-folder 1/30)
- Subject files re: funding for education, 1965-1967 (Box-folder 1/31)
- Subject files re: various constitutional issues, 1968 (Box-folder 1/32)
- Subject files re: Interchange, undated (Box-folder 1/33)
- Subject files re: Intiative 208 establishing joint tenancy to simplify inheritance by avoiding probate costs, 1962 (Box-folder 1/34)
- Publicity and biographical information about Lennart at the time of his retirement, 1967 (Box-folder 1/35)
- Republican Party platform information, 1960-1966 (Box-folder 1/36)
- "Skagit Deal" materials re: issues facing Western Washington PUDs purchase of Puget Sound Power and Light properties, circa 1949 (Box-folder 1/37)
- Essays, reports and letters concerning taxation issues, 1953-1967 (Box-folder 1/38)
- Speeches by Lennart re: the United States and Washington State constitutions, 1963 (Box-folder 1/39)
- Talks by Lennart on KPUG Radio re: current legislative issues, 1967 (Box-folder 1/40)
- Speeches by Lennart re: patriotism, undated (Box-folder 1/41)
- Speeches given by Lennart to the Republican Party (possibly at the Washington State Republican Convention), 1967 (Box-folder 1/42)
- Lennart retirement speeches, 1967 (Box-folder 1/43)
- Speeches by Lennart re: taxation, undated (Box-folder 1/44)
- Speeches by Lennart re: ethics in government, 1965 (Box-folder 1/45)
- Miscellaneous speeches, circa 1960s (Box-folder 1/46)
- Speeches by others re: governor's fiscal message, 1965 (Box-folder 1/47)
- Speeches by others on various subjects, 1967 (Box-folder 1/48)
- Washington Education publication, 1963 (Box-folder 1/49)
- Clippings, including Lennart's obituary, 1957-1968 (Box-folder 1/50-1/51)
- Ephemera, 1955-1968 (Box-folder 1/52-1/54)
- Publications and letters concerning the Washington State Arts Commission, 1967 (Box-folder 1/55)
- Children's Home Society materials, 1968 (Box-folder 1/56)
- Puget Sound PCA materials, 1967 (Box-folder 1/57)
- Materials related to Lennart's farm business (seed potatoes), 1953; 1962-1964 (Box-folder 1/58-1/59)
- Washington State College Foundation, 1966-1967 (Box-folder 1/60)